So we spent sometimes like
two months training the bots
on thousands of CPUs,
terabytes of memory sometimes.
But when it came
time to actually play
against the humans, they
would act almost instantly.
It was just a lookup table.
And the humans, when they
were in a tough spot,
they would not act
instantly, they would think.
They would sit there and they
would think for five seconds,
maybe five minutes if it was
a really difficult decision.
And it was clear that was
allowing them to come up
with better strategies.
And so I wanted to investigate
this behavior in our bots.
If we could add this to our
bots, how much of a difference
would it make?
The ability to, instead
of acting instantly
to take some time and
compute a better strategy
for the spot that
the agent was in.
And this is what I found.
So on the x-axis here, we
have the number of buckets.
You can think of this
as like the number
of parameters in your model.
And on the y-axis, we have
distance from Nash equilibrium.
So this is basically
like how much you would
lose to a worst case adversary.
So the lower this number is,
the better your poker bot is.
And you can see, as you scale
up the number of parameters,
your performance improves.
And as you increase the number
parameters by about 100x,
your exploitability
goes down by about half.
And indeed, you're getting
a much better poker bot.
But you can see,
the blue line here
is if you don't have
search, and the orange line
is if you do add search.
And you can see,
just adding search,
adding the ability to sit
there and think for a bit
improved the performance
of these models
and it reduced the
exploitability,
the distance from Nash
equilibrium by about 7x.
And if you were to extend that
blue line and see how many
parameters would you need
in order to be comparable
to adding search, the answer
is you would need to scale up
your model by about 100,000x.
So this was pretty mind-blowing
to me when I saw this.
Over the course of my PhD, the
first three years, first three
or four years in my PhD,
I managed to scale up
these models by about 100x.
And I was proud of that.
I mean, that's a pretty
impressive result, I think.
But what this plot was showing
me was that just adding search
was the equivalent of scaling
things up by about 100,000x.
And so all of my previous
research up until this point
would just be a footnote
compared to adding search.
So when I saw this,
it became clear.
This was the answer to
beating top humans poker.
And so for the next
year, basically nonstop,
I worked on scaling search.
Now, there's a question
that naturally comes up,
which is why wasn't
this considered before?
There's a few factors.
So first of all, I should
say search had been
considered in poker before.
And it's actually quite
natural to say, well,
if you had search
in chess and search
in Go, why would you not
consider search in poker?
There's a few reasons.
One is that, culturally,
the poker research
grew out of game theory
and reinforcement learning.
And so it wasn't really
from the same background
as the people that are working
on chess and working on Go.
When you scale search,
scaling test on compute,
it makes all your experiments
much more expensive and just
more unpleasant to work with.
And there were just
incentive structures.
I mean, people always
thinking about winning
the next annual computer
poker competition.
And the ACPC limited
the resources
that you could use at test time.
So search wasn't really possible
effectively in the ACPC.
And I think the biggest
factor is that people just
didn't think it would make
such a huge difference.
I mean, I think it's
reasonable to look at something
like search and think
like, oh, yeah, that might
make a 10x difference.
You probably wouldn't think
it makes 100,000x difference.
And so there were some
people working on it,
but it wasn't really the focus
of a lot of people's research.
So anyway, focused on
scaling search, and that
led to the 2017 Brains versus
AI competition where we again
played our bot against
four top poker pros.
120,000 hands of poker,
$200,000 in prize money.
And this time, the bot won
by 15 big blinds per 100
instead of nine
big blinds per 100.
This was a crushing victory.
Each team lost
individually to the bot
and four standard deviations
of statistical significance.
We followed this up in 2019
with a Six-Player Poker AI
competition.
The big difference here
is that we figured out
how to do depth-limited search.
So before the 2017 bot, it
would always have the search
to the end of the game.
Here, it only had to do
search a few moves ahead
and you can stop there.
And so this time, again, it won
with statistical significance.
And what's really
surprising about this bot
is that despite it being
a much larger game,
the six-player poker bot
Pluribus cost under $150
to train on cloud
computing resources.
And it runs on 28 CPU
cores at different time.
There's no GPUs.
So I think what this
shows is that this really
wasn't algorithmic improvement.
I mean, this would have
been doable 20 years ago
if people knew how to do it.
And I think it also shows
the power of search.
If you can figure
out how to scale,
that compute at
test time, it really
can make a huge difference and
bring down your training costs
by huge amount.
Anyway, so I want to say also,
this is not limited to poker.
If you look at Go, you
see a similar pattern.
So this is a plot from
the AlphaGo Zero paper.
On the x-axis, we have
different versions of AlphaGo
and on the y-axis,
we have Elo rating,
which is a way of
comparing different bots
but also a way of
comparing bots to humans.
And you can see, if--
so super human performance
is around 3,600 Elo.
And you can see AlphaGo
lead the version that played
against Lisa Dole in 2016.
That's right over the line
of superhuman performance.
AlphaGo zero, the strongest
version of AlphaGo,
is around 5200 Elo.
But if you take out
the test time search,
if you just play according
to the policy net
and not do any Monte Carlo tree
search in AlphaGo Zero at test
time, then the Elo rating
drops to around 3,000,
which is substantially below
expert human performance.
So what this shows is that if
you take out Monte Carlo tree
search at test time, the
AlphaGo Zero is not superhuman.
And in fact, nobody
has made a superhuman
Go bot that does not
use search in some form.
Nobody has made a
raw neural network
that can beat top humans in Go.
And I should say also, this
is just if you're taking out
the search at test time.
I'm not even talking about
taking it out of training time.
If you took it out
of training time,
it wouldn't even
get off the ground.
Now, there's a question
of, OK, well, surely you
could just scale up
the model, scale up
the amount of training,
and you would eventually
surpass superhuman performance
and match the performance
if you added search.
And that's true, yes.
If you scale up the models and
if you scale up the training,
then you would eventually match
the performance with search.
But there's a
question of how much
would you have to
scale it up by?
Now, a rough rule of
thumb is that in order
to increase your Elo
rating by about 120 points,
you either have to double
the amount of model size
and training or you have to
double the amount of test time
search.
So if you look at that gap of
around 2000 Elo points and you
calculate the number of
doublings that you would need,
the answer is that in order
to get the raw policy net from
3,000 to 5,200 Elo, you would
need to scale your model
and your training
by about 100,000x.
So why is this important?
I think you look at
what's happening today
with large language
models and transformers
and you see something similar.
I mean you're getting huge--
there's a question of,
what do I mean by search?
There's specific
kinds of search,
like Monte Carlo tree search,
the ability to just plan ahead
what you're going to do instead
of just acting instantly based
on your pre-computed policy.
But really, what I mean
by search more broadly
is the ability to scale
the amount of computation
to get better performance.
I think that's the real
value that search is adding.
Instead of just acting
according to your pre-computed--
front-loading all
of your computation,
so that you're
doing everything--
all your computation
ahead of time
and then add inference time
acting basically instantly.
Could you get a
better solution if you
had five minutes to
output an action instead
of 100 milliseconds?
So, yeah, I think you look at--
sorry, there's a question.
Does a transformer with a
search circuit count as search
or do you mean hand
engineering search algos?
I don't want to get bogged
down into the details
of how to do this because the
answer is nobody really knows
yet.
Nobody really has a general
way of doing search.
In all the domains that we've
done search successfully,
like poker and Go, it's done in
a fairly domain-specific way.
Go use this algorithm called
Monte Carlo tree search.
And yeah, I guess you
could think of beam search
as like one simple
form of search.
But it does seem
like there should
be better ways in the future.
So anyway, where
I'm going with this
is look at how large language
models are being trained today.
And you're seeing
millions of dollars
being thrown at pre-training.
I wouldn't be surprised
if we see a large language
model that would cost
$100 million to train.
We might even get
to $1,000,000,000.
But the inference cost is
still going to be very small.
And so there's a
question of, could you
do substantially better if
you could scale the amount
of inference cost as well?
You may amortize some
of your training cost.
So there's this lecture
called the Bitter Lesson
by Richard Sutton that says,
"The biggest lesson that
can be learned--" and so
it's a really great essay.
I recommend reading it.
But one of the big
takeaways is he
says, "The biggest lesson that
can be learned from over 70
years of AI research
is that general methods
that leverage computation are
ultimately the most effective.
The two methods that seem to
scale arbitrarily in this way
are search and learning."
Now, I think we've done a great
job with generalizing search--
sorry, generalizing learning.
And I think that there is
still room for improvement
when it comes to search.
And yeah, the next goal
really is about generality.
Can we develop a truly general
way of scaling inference
compute instead of just doing
things like Monte Carlo tree
search that are
specific to a better
domain-- to a specific domain,
and also better than things
like chain of thought?
What this would look like is
that you have much higher test
time compute.
But you have much
more capable models.
And I think for certain domains,
that trade off is worth it.
If you think about
what inference
cost we're willing to pay
for a proof of the Riemann
hypothesis, I think we'd
be willing to pay a lot.
Or the cost of--
what cost are we willing to
pay for new lifesaving drugs?
I think we'd be
willing to pay a lot.
So I think that there
is an opportunity here.
Anyway, so that's in prelude--
I guess, any
questions about that
before I move on to Cicero?
By the way, the reason
why I'm talking about this
is because it's going to inform
the approach that we took
to Cicero, which
I think is quite
different from the approach
that a lot of other researchers
might have taken
to this problem.
Someone asks, can you
give an example of search?
Well, Monte Carlo tree
search is one form of search.
You can also think of breadth
for search, depth for search,
these kinds of things.
They're all search.
I would also argue
that chain of thought
is doing something
similar to search
where it's allowing the model to
leverage extra compute at test
time to get better performance.
But I think that
that's the main thing
that you want, the ability to
leverage extra compute at test
time.
What's the search--
what's the space
that you are searching over?
Again, in a game like Go, it's
different board positions.
But you could also
imagine searching
over different sentences that
you could say things like that.
There's a lot of
flexibility there as well.
So now, I want to
get into Cicero.
So first thing I should say
when it comes to Cicero,
this is a big team effort.
This is actually one
of the great things
about working on this
project, that there was just
such a diverse talent pool
experts in reinforcement
learning, planning, game theory,
natural language processing,
all working together on this.
And it would not have been
possible without everybody.
So the motivation for Diplomacy
actually came from 2019.
We were looking at
all the breakthroughs
that were happening at the time.
And I think a good example of
this XKCD comic that came out
in 2012 that shows different
categories games, games that
are solved, games where
computers can beat
top humans, games for computers
to lose to top humans,
and games where computers
may never outplay top humans.
And in this category
of computers
to lose to top humans, you had
four games, Go, Arimaa, poker,
and StarCraft.
In 2015, actually, one of
my colleagues, David Wu,
made the first AI to beat
top humans in Arimaa.
In 2016, we have AlphaGo
beating Lisa Dole on Go.
In 2017, you have the work
that I just described where
we beat top humans in poker.
And in 2019, we had an
AlphaStar beating expert humans
in StarCraft.
So that shows the incredible
amount of progress
that had happened in
strategic reasoning
over the past several
years leading up to 2019.
And at the same time, we also
had GPT-2 come out in 2019.
And it showed that language
model and natural language
processing was
progressing much faster
than I think a lot of people,
including us, expected.
And so we were
thinking about what--
after the six-player
poker work, I
was discussing
with my colleagues
what should we work on next?
And we were throwing around
different domains to work on.
And given the incredible
amount of progress in AI,
we wanted to pick
something really ambitious,
something that we
thought you couldn't just
tackle by scaling up
existing approaches,
that you really needed something
new in order to address.
And we landed on
Diplomacy because we
thought that it would be the
hardest game to make an AI for.
So what is Diplomacy?
Diplomacy is a natural
language strategy game.
It takes place right
before World War I.
You play as one of the seven
great powers of Europe,
England, France, Germany,
Austria, Russia, and Turkey.
And your goal is to control
the majority of the map.
In practice that
rarely happens, if you
control a majority of
the map then you've
won, in practice, nobody
ends up winning outright.
And so your score is
proportional to the percentage
of the map that you control.
Now, what's really
interesting about Diplomacy
is that it is a natural
language negotiation game.
So you have these conversations,
like what you're seeing here
between Germany and England
where they will privately
communicate with each other
before making their moves.
And so you can have Germany
ask, want to support Sweden?
England says, let me
think on that, and so on.
So this is a popular strategy
game developed in the 1950s.
It was JFK and Kissinger's
favorite game actually.
And like I said,
each turn involves
sophisticated private natural
language negotiations.
And I want to make clear,
this is not negotiations
like you would see in a
game like Settlers of Catan,
for example.
You're seeing-- it's
much more like Survivor,
if you've ever seen
the TV show Survivor.
You have discussions
around alliances
that you'd like to
build, discussions
around specific
tactics that you'd
like to execute on the current
turn, and also more long-term
strategy around where
do we go from here
and how do we divide resources.
Now, the way the game works,
you have these negotiations
that lasts between 5 and
15 minutes, depending
on the version of the
game on each turn.
And all these negotiations
are done privately,
pairwise negotiation.
Also, I think that
you are not muted.
Thank you.
And then after the
negotiation period completes,
everybody will simultaneously
write down their moves.
And so a player could
promise you something like,
I'm going to support you into
this territory in this turn.
But then when people actually
write down their moves,
they might not write that down.
And so you only find out if
they were true to their word
when all the moves are
revealed simultaneously.
And so for this reason,
alliances and trust-building
is key, the ability
to trust that somebody
is going to follow
through on their promises.
That's really what
this game is all about.
And the ability
to convince people
that you are going to follow
through on your promises
is really what this
game is all about.
And so for this
reason, Diplomacy
has long been considered a
challenge problem for AI.
This research and the game
going back to the 80s,
the research really
only picked up--
it picked up quite
intensely starting in 2019
when researchers from DeepMind,
ourselves, Mila, other places
started working on this.
Now, a lot of that research--
the vast majority
of that research
actually was focused on
the non-language version
of the game, which was
seen as a stepping stone
to the full natural
language version.
Though we decided to
focus from the start
on the full natural language
version of the game.
So to give you a sense of what
these negotiations and dialogue
look like, here is one example.
So here, England, you can
see they move their fleet
in Norway to Saint Petersburg.
And that occupies the
Russian territory.
And so this is what
the border state
looks like after that move.
And now, there's
this conversation
between Austria and Russia.
Austria says, well,
what happened up North?
Russia says, England stabbed.
I'm afraid that they may
be closer to me, my friend.
Austria says,
yeah, that's rough.
Are you going to be OK up there?
Russia says, I hope so.
England seems to still
want to work together.
Austria says, can you
make a deal with Germany?
So the players
are now discussing
what should be discussed
with other players.
Russia says, good idea.
Then Austria says,
you'll be fine as long
as you can defend Sevastopol.
So Sevastopol is this
territory down to the South.
You can see that Turkey has a
fleet and an army in the Black
Sea in Armenia
next to Sevastopol.
And so they could potentially
attack that territory
next turn.
Austria says, can you
support hold Sevastopol
with Ukraine and Romania?
I'll support hold Romania.
Russia says, yep,
I'm already doing so.
Austria says, awesome.
Hopefully, we can start
getting you back on your feet.
So this is an example of
the kinds of conversations
that you'll see in
a game of Diplomacy.
In this conversation, Austria
is actually our bot Cicero.
So that kind of gives you a
sense of the sophistication
of the agents dialogue.
OK, I'll skip this for--
so I guess I'll go into this.
I don't want to take
up too much time.
Really, what makes
diplomacy interesting
is that support is key.
So here, for example,
Budapest and Warsaw, the red
and the purple units both
try to move into Galicia.
And so since it's
a one versus one,
they both bounced
back and neither
moves into the territory.
In the middle panel, you can
see Vienna supports Budapest
into Galicia.
And so now, it's
a two versus one.
And that red unit will
indeed enter Galicia.
And what's really
interesting about Diplomacy
is that it doesn't just have
to be your own units that
are supporting you, it could be
another player's units as well.
So for example, the green player
could support the red player
into Galicia, and then that red
unit would still go in there.
So support is really what
the game is all about,
and negotiating over support.
And so for that
reason, Diplomacy
has this reputation as the
game that ruins friendships.
It's really difficult to have
an alliance with somebody
for three or four hours and
then have them backstab you,
and basically just
ruin your game.
But if you talk to
expert Diplomacy players,
they view it differently.
They say diplomacy is
ultimately about building trust
in an environment that
encourages you to not trust
anyone.
And that's why we decided
to work on the game.
Could we make an AI that
is able to build trust
with the players in an
environment that encourages
them to not trust anybody?
Can the bot honestly
communicate that it's
going to do something
and evaluate
whether another person
is being honest when
they are saying that they're
going to do something?
So why Diplomacy?
It's this nice intersection
of reinforcement
learning and planning,
and also natural language.
There's two perspectives that
we can take on why Diplomacy
is a really interesting domain.
One is the multi-agent
perspective.
So here, all the previous
gaming AI results,
like chess, Go,
poker, these have all
been in purely zero sum--
two-player zero-sum domains.
And in these
domains, self-play is
guaranteed to converge
to an optimal solution.
Basically, what
this means is you
can start having the bot
play completely from scratch
with no human data.
And by playing against
itself repeatedly,
it will eventually converge
to this unbeatable optimal
solution called the
Minimax equilibrium.
But that result only holds
in two-player zero-sum games.
That whole paradigm only holds
When you go to domains
that involve cooperation,
in addition to
competition, then success
requires understanding human
behavior and conventions.
You can't just treat the other
players like machines anymore.
You have to treat
them like humans.
You have to model
human irrationality,
human suboptimality.
One example of this
is actually language.
You can imagine if you were
to train a bot completely
from scratch in the
game of Diplomacy,
the full natural language
version of the game,
there's no reason why
the bot would learn
to communicate in English.
It would learn to communicate
in some weird gibberish robot
language.
And then when you stick it
in a game with six humans,
it's not going to be able
to cooperate with them.
So we have to find a way
to incorporate human data
and be able to learn how
humans behave in order
to succeed in this game.
There's also the
NLP perspective,
which is that current language
models are essentially
just imitating human-like text.
Now, there's been some
progress with things like RLHF.
But that's still not really the
way that humans communicate.
They communicate with
an intention in mind.
They come up with this
intention and then
they communicate with
the goal of communicating
that intention.
And they understand that others
are trying to do the same.
And so there's a
question of, can we
move beyond chitchat to
grounded intentional dialogue?
So Cicero is an AI
agent for Diplomacy
that integrates high level
strategic play and open domain
dialogue.
And we use 50,000 human
games of Diplomacy
acquired through a
partnership with the website
webdiplomacy.net.
So we entered Cicero in an
online diplomacy league,
just to give you the
results up front.
Cicero was not
detected as an AI agent
for 40 games with
82 unique players.
There was one player that
mentioned after the fact that--
they kind of made a joke
about us being a bot.
But they didn't
really follow up on it
and nobody else
followed up on it.
And they later accused somebody
else of also being a bot.
So we weren't sure how seriously
to take that accusation.
But I think it's safe to say
it made it through all 40 games
without being detected as bot.
And then in fact, when we
told the players afterwards
that it was a bot
the whole time,
these are the kinds of
responses that we got.
People were quite surprised,
pleasantly surprised,
fortunately.
Nobody was upset with us.
But they were quite
surprised that there
was a bot that had
been playing this game
within the whole time.
So in terms of
results, Cicero placed
in the top 10% of players.
It's a high variance game.
And so if you look at players
that played five or more games,
it placed 2nd out of 19.
And it achieved more than
double the average human score.
So I would describe
this as a strong level
of human performance.
I wouldn't go as far as to
say that this is superhuman,
by any means.
But it is currently
quite a strong result.
Now, to give you a picture
of how Cicero works.
So the input that we
feed into the model
is the board state and
the recent action history.
That's shown at
the top left here,
and also the dialogue that it's
had with all the players up
until now.
So that's going to get fed into
a dialogue conditional action
model that's going to
predict what Cicero thinks
all the players are
going to do this turn
and what they think
we will do this turn.
These leads what we call
anchor policies that
are then used for planning.
Now, planning here,
again, this is
like the part where we leverage
extra compute at test time
in order to get
better performance.
So essentially, we take
these initial predictions
of what everybody's
going to do, what
are called anchor policies.
And we improve upon these
predictions using this planning
process called piKL,
where basically we
account for the fact
that players will pick
actions that have
higher expected value
with higher probability.
We're essentially adding
this rationality prior
to all the players to
assume that they're not
going to blunder as often
as the model might suggest,
and they're going to pick
smarter actions with higher
probability than the
initial model might suggest.
And what we find is that
this actually gives us
a better prediction of
what all the players will
do than just relying on
the raw neural net itself.
This gives us the action that
we actually play in the game.
And it also gives us
what we call "intense."
So intense are an
action for ourselves
and an action for the dialogue
partner that we're speaking to.
And now, we have this
dialogue conditional--
so we have this dialogue
model that conditions on these
"intense."
So the intense are fed into
the dialogue model along
with the board state and action
history, and also the dialogue
that we've had so far.
And that dialogue
model will then
generate candidate
messages that our
conditioned on those intense.
These candidate messages
go through a series
of filters that
filter out nonsense,
grounding issues, and also
low expected value action--
low expected value messages.
And ultimately, we
get out a message
to send to our dialogue partner.
Now, every time we send
or receive a message,
we will repeat
this whole process.
So there's actually a lot
that is quite novel in Cicero.
And I'm going to try to
talk about the contributions
as much as possible.
I might go through
this a little quickly.
So we have time for questions.
The first one is a
controllable dialogue model
that conditions
on the game state
and a set of intended
actions for the speaker
and the recipient.
So I have a question,
what is the action
space here for the model?
The action space for the
action prediction model
is like all the actions that
you could take in the game--
that a player could
take in the game.
For the dialogue model,
it's like messages
that you can send.
Got it.
So-- one second.
OK.
So we train what we call
an intent model that
predicts what actions
people will take
at the end of truthful turns.
Basically, what we're trying
to predict, what are people
intending to do when they
communicate a certain message?
And then we use this to
automatically annotate
the data set with
basically what we
expect people's intentions were
when they sent that message.
And we filter out--
we filter out as much as
possible lies from the data
set, so that the
text of the data set
is annotated with the
truthful intention.
And then during play, Cicero
conditions the dialogue model
on the truthful intention
that it intends to take.
And the goal then is
that-- the hope then
is that it will
generate a message
consistent with that intention.
And that is then fed
into everything else.
Sorry, the intentions that
we generate through planning
are fed into the dialogue model.
So to give you an example
of what this looks like,
this gives us a way to
control the dialogue model
through a set of intentions.
Here, we are-- Cicero
is England in pink
and their action is to move to
Belgium, among other things.
And so, if we feed this
intention into the dialogue
model, then the message
that might get generated
is something like
England saying to France,
do you mind supporting me--
do you mind supporting
Edi to Belgium?
On the other hand, let's
say Cicero's action is
to support France into Belgium.
Then if you feed that
into the dialogue model,
then the message
that's generated
might say something like,
let me know if you want
me to support you to Belgium.
Otherwise, I'll
probably poke Holland.
Now, what we find is that
conditioning the dialogue
model on these
intentions in this way,
it makes the model
more controllable,
but it also leads
to higher quality
dialogue with less nonsense.
So we found that
it led to dialogue
that was more consistent
with the state,
more consistent with the
plan, higher quality, lower
perplexity.
And I think the argument--
the reasoning for why
this is the case is
that we're kind of we're
leaving the dialogue model the
burden of having to come up
with a good strategy.
We're allowing
the dialogue model
to do what it does best,
to focus on what it
does best, which is dialogue.
And we're relieving it of
the strategic components
of the game.
Because we're feeding that
strategy into the dialogue
model.
So that's one main
contribution, this
control the dialogue model
that conditions on a plan.
The second is a
planning engine that
accounts for dialogue
and human behavior.
So I mentioned that a lot
of previous work on games
was done using self-play in
two-player zero-sum settings.
Now, the problem
with pure self-play
is that it can learn
strong policies
but it doesn't stick
with human conventions,
and it can't account
for dialogue.
It's just going to ignore the
human data and the human way
of playing if you
just do self-play.
So that's one extreme.
The other extreme
that you can go
is to just do supervised
learning on human data,
create this model
of how humans play,
and then train with
those imitation humans.
And if you do
this, you'll end up
with a bot that's
consistent with dialogue
and human conventions.
But it's only as strong
as the training data.
And we found that
it was actually
very easily manipulable
through adversarial dialogue.
So for example, you can
send messages to it saying,
thanks for agreeing to
support me at the Paris.
And it will think
like, well, I've
only ever seen that
message in my training data
when I've agreed to support
the person to the Paris.
And so I guess I'm supporting
them at the Paris this turn,
even though that might be a
terrible move for the bot.
So I came up with this
algorithm called piKL
that it kind of is a happy
medium between these two
extremes.
The way piKL works is it's
basically trying to-- it's
doing self-play but
regularized toward sticking
to the human imitation policy.
So it has a KL
penalty for deviating
from the human imitation policy.
So we have this
parameter lambda that
controls how easy
it is to deviate
from the human
invitation policy.
At lambda equals zero, it just
ignores the human imitation
policy completely and
just does pure self-play.
And so it just do self-play
as if from scratch
at lambda equals zero.
At lambda equals
infinity, it's just
playing the human
invitation policy
and not doing self-play at all.
But for intermediate values
of lambda, what we find
is that it actually
gives you a good medium
between sticking to
human conventions
and performing strongly.
So you can kind of see
this behavior emerge here.
So there's a question.
Is this similar to offline RL or
also incorporates exploration?
So let's say, there's
actually a lot
of similar work on
having a KL penalty.
And so yes, I would
say that it's very
similar to a lot of that work.
It's also been done
actually in AlphaStar
where they had a KL penalty.
Though that was more
about aiding exploration,
like using human data
to aid exploration,
rather than trying to
better imitate humans.
So I think what's interesting
about the piKL work
is that, one, we
find it imitates
humans better than just doing
supervised learning alone.
And two, we are doing
a bit of theory of mind
where we assume that the
other players are also--
we're using this as a model for
our behavior, what we expect
other people to
think our behavior
is in addition to modeling
the other players.
So it's like a
common knowledge--
common knowledge
like an algorithm
that we're using here.
So the kind of behavior
that you see from this,
you can see here, let's
say England agrees--
sorry, so let's say
we're in this situation.
This actually came
up in a real game.
And it inspired a
figure from our paper.
So England and
France are fighting.
France is the bot.
And France asks if England
is willing to disengage.
And let's say
England says, yes, I
will move out of English
channel if you head back to NAO.
Well, we can see that Cicero
does in fact back off, leaves--
goes to NAO, and the
disengagement is successful.
And so this shows that
the bot strategy really
is reflecting the
dialogue that it's
had with this other player.
Another message that
England might send
is something like,
I'm sorry, you've
been fighting me
this whole game.
I can't trust you that
you won't stab me.
And so in this case, Cicero will
continue its attack on England.
And you can see again,
this is reflective-- it's
changing its behavior
depending on the dialogue.
But you can also have
this kind of message
where England, says,
yes, I'll leave
English channel if you move into
Munich and Holland to Belgium.
So these are really bad
moves for Cicero to follow.
And so if you just use-- if
you just look at the raw policy
net, it might actually do this.
It might actually do these moves
because England suggested it.
But because we're using
piKL that incorporates--
it counts for these expected
value different actions,
it will actually partially
back off but ignore
the suggested moves
because it recognize
that those will leave it
very vulnerable to an attack.
I'll skip the slide for time.
Another thing I should
say is that we're not just
doing planning.
We're actually doing this in
a full self-play reinforcement
learning loop.
And again, the goal here is--
it's really about modeling
humans better than supervised
learning alone.
And we found that doing
this self-play reinforcement
learning with piKL allowed us
to better model human behavior
than just doing
imitation learning.
Finally, we have an ensemble
of message filtering techniques
that filters both nonsensical
and strategically unsound
messages.
So to give you an example of
what these filters look like,
one that we developed is
value-based filtering.
So the motivation
for this is that what
we feed into our
dialogue model is
a plan for ourselves and
for our speaking partner,
but it's the entire plan
that we have for ourselves.
And so we might end up feeding
into the dialogue model
the fact that we're going to
attack the player that we're
speaking to.
Now, the dialogue model is,
to be honest, kind of dumb.
And it doesn't really
know that it shouldn't
be telling this
player that they're
going to be attacked this turn.
And so you have
these messages that
might be sent, something like
the second one shown here
where England says to France,
we have hostile intentions
towards you.
You must be wiped
from the board.
Please provide a croissant.
So this is actually a message
that the bot sends to a player.
Not to a player, this was
preliminary testing and kind
of motivated this
whole approach.
So we don't want the bot to
send these kinds of messages
if it's going to
attack a player.
We want it to send
something that's
not an outright lie necessarily,
but just something--
either not send a
message or send something
that's much more bland.
And so we filter out
these kinds of messages
by looking at the value.
What we do is we generate a
bunch of candidate messages,
and then we see if we
were to send this message,
what is the behavior
that we would expect
the other players to take?
What actions will
we expect them to do
after we send this message?
And what do they expect we will
do after we send this message?
And then we see, what
is the expected value
of the action that
we intend to take
given the prediction of what
everybody else is going to do?
So if our intention
is to attack France,
then we can see, well, if I were
to send this message to France,
then they're going to
get really defensive
and defend against
an attack from us,
and our attack is going
to be unsuccessful.
And so therefore, I probably
shouldn't send this message
to them.
And so in this way,
we can actually
filter out messages that
have low expected value.
We found that this
worked surprisingly well.
Dialogue examples, I'll
go through one just
for the sake of time.
So here we have Cicero's France.
And Francis saying--
France is conversing with
Turkey, who's a human player.
And they're debating over
who's going to get Tunis,
this territory circled in red.
You can see they both have
fleets next to the territory.
If they both go for it, neither
of them are going to get it.
And so they need to work
out some sort of deal.
So France says, I'll work with
you, but I need Tunis for now.
Turkey says, nope, you've
got to let me have it.
France says, no, I need it.
And then France
suggests, you can
take these other
territories instead.
You have Serbia
and Rome to take.
Turkey says, they're
impossible targets.
And then Cicero
suggests specific moves
that would allow Turkey to
capture these territories.
So Cicero says, Greece to
Ionian, Ionian to Iranian.
Turkey says, hmm, you're
right, good ideas.
And then France says,
and then in the fall,
you take Rome and
Austria collapses.
And so that allows Turkey to
make progress against Austria,
but conveniently it also
allows France to capture Tunis
because Turkey will be using
those units for something else.
So limitations and
future directions,
intent representation is
just an action per player.
So there's a question
of, the intentions
that we're feeding
into the dialogue model
is an action that we're
going to take for this turn
and for the next
turn, for ourselves
and for the other player.
But ideally, we would have
a richer set of intentions.
We would be able to condition on
things like long-term strategy
or style of communication
or asking questions.
That's one of the
limitations of this approach.
Now of course, the richer you
make the space of intentions,
the more room there is
for things to go wrong.
And you also have to
then train the model
to be able to handle these
wider space of intentions.
There is a question, do you
think the dialogue model is
learning an internal model--
internal world model to be
so good at predicting moves?
No, we're-- this is arguably
why we're conditioning
on intentions.
We're relieving
the dialogue model
of having to come up
with a good world model
because we're telling
it, these are the moves
that we are planning
to take this turn,
and these are the moves that
we would like this other player
to take this turn.
So we're like-- we're able
to have the world model
separate from the dialogue model
but condition on the output
from the world model.
Another limitation is
that Cicero's value model
doesn't condition on dialogue.
And so it has a
limited understanding
of the long-term
effects of dialogue.
This greatly limits our ability
to plan what kind of messages
we should be sending.
And this is actually why
we always conditioned
Cicero's dialogue generation
on its truthful intentions.
You could argue that there is
situations in Diplomacy where
you would want to lie
to the other player.
The best players rarely lie,
but they do lie sometimes.
And you have to understand the
trade off between if you lie,
you are going to not--
it's going to be
much harder to work
with this person in the future.
And so you have to make sure
that the value that you're
getting positionally is
worth that loss of trust
and that broken relationship.
Now, because
Cicero's value model
doesn't condition on
dialogue, it can't really
understand this trade off.
And so for this reason, we
actually always condition it
on its truthful intentions.
No, it is possible to
have Cicero's value
model conditioned on dialogue,
but you would need way
more data and it would make
things much more expensive.
And so we weren't able to
do it further for this bot.
And finally, there's
a big question
that I mentioned
earlier, which is,
is there a more general way of
scaling inference time compute
to achieve better performance?
The way that we've
done planning in Cicero
is, I would argue, a
bit domain specific.
I think it's like-- the idea
of piKL is quite general.
But I think that there are
potentially more general ways
of doing planning.
Somebody is asking,
looking forward
to the next two to three years.
What criteria will you use
to select the next game
to try to conquer?
Honestly, like I said,
we chose Diplomacy
because we thought it
would be the hardest
game to make an AI for.
And I think that that's true.
I don't think that we're going
to be working on games anymore
because I can't think
of any other game
that if we were to
succeed at that,
it would be truly impressive.
And so I think where the
research is going in the future
is generality.
Instead of getting AI to
play this specific game,
can we get an AI that is
able to play Diplomacy,
but could also play Go
or poker, or could also
write essays and stories,
and solve math problems
and write theorems?
I think what we
will see is games
serving as benchmarks for
progress but not as the goal.
It'll be part of
the test set but not
part of the training set.
And I think that's the way
it should be going forward.
Finally, I want to
add that Diplomacy
is an amazing testbed
for multi-agent AI
in grounded dialogue.
So if you are interested
in these kinds of domains,
I highly recommend taking
advantage of the fact
that we are--
we've open-sourced all
of our code and models.
And the dialogue
and action data is
available through what's
called an RFP, where
you can apply to get access
to the dialogue and data.
So thanks for listening.
To wrap up, Cicero combines
strategic reasoning
and natural language
in Diplomacy.
It placed in the top
10% of human players.
And the paper is in
science, and code and models
are publicly
available at this URL.
So thanks.
And for the remaining
time, I'll take questions.
Thanks a lot.
So we'll also open some
questions from the class.
We can finish their
Zoom questions.
So if anyone has
some questions, I
think now you can answer those.
Yeah, there's one question,
are you concerned about AIs
out-competing humans at
real-world diplomatic strategic
negotiation and deception tasks?
So like I said, we're not
very focused on deception,
even though arguably
deception is a part
of the game of Diplomacy.
I think for diplomatic
and strategic negotiation,
I don't--
look, the way that
we've developed Cicero,
it's designed to play
Diplomacy, the game of Diplomacy
specifically, and you can't
use it out-of-the-box for other
tasks.
That said, I do think that the
techniques are quite general.
And so hopefully,
others can build
on that and to be able
to do different things.
And I think it is
entirely possible
that over the next
several years,
you will see this entering
into real-world negotiations
much more often.
I actually think
that Diplomacy is
a big step towards real-world
applicability compared
to breakthroughs in
games like Go and poker.
Because now, your
action space is really
like the space of
natural language,
and you have to
model human behavior.
Do you think in the future we
could appoint an AI to the UN
council?
Hopefully, only if it
does better than humans.
But that would be very
interesting to see.
I'm also curious, what's the
future things that you're
working on in this direction?
Do you think you
can do something
like AlphaGo Zero where you
just take this piKL model
and then just be
giving self-play?
Or what sort of
future actions are
you thinking for improving
this sort of bots?
I think the future
directions are really
focused around generality.
I think one of the
big insights of Cicero
is this ability to
leverage planning
to get better performance
with language models
and in this strategic domain.
I think there's a
lot of opportunity
to do that sort of thing in
a broader space of domains.
I mean, you look at
language models today,
and they do
token-by-token prediction.
And I think there's a big
opportunity to go beyond that.
So that's what I'm
excited to look into.
I'm also curious, I didn't
understand the exact details
how using planning or Monte
Carlo tree search with your--
like the models that you have.
So is it like--
We didn't use Monte Carlo
tree search in Cicero.
Monte Carlo tree search
is very good heuristic,
but it's a heuristic
that is particularly
useful for deterministic
perfect information games.
And I think in order to have a
truly general form of planning,
we need to go more abstract
than Monte Carlo tree search.
We use this algorithm called
piKL based on a regret
minimization algorithm.
I don't really want to
go into the details of it
because it's not that
important for the class.
But the idea is it is this
iterative algorithm that
will gradually refine the
prediction of what everybody's
going to do and get better and
better predictions the more
iterations that you're on.
And that's in the research?
Yup.
Correct.
Yeah.
Go for it, you're unmuted.
So yeah, my question
is when we were talking
about generability, how
does the communication
between different
modules of the model look
like, particularly when we're
talking about the dialogue
model?
How do you send information
from the policy network
to the dialogue model?
And in the future, if
you have a model that's
good at different
tasks, are we going
to have a really big policy
net that learns all of them
or separate language
modules for all of them?
How do you break it down?
So we actually
convert the policy
by the action for ourselves
and for our dialogue partner
into a string--
natural language string
and to speed that
into the dialogue model
along with all the dialogue
that it's had so far.
So it's just all
text in, text out.
And that works great.
And then, what was the
second part of your question?
Something like,
are we just going
to have one giant policy
net to learn everything?
Yeah.
It was like so, if you're
only using text first,
doesn't it limit the model?
And if you're using it
for different games,
are you thinking
like, what do you
say in the future you will
work on generalizability?
Are you thinking about
a big policy network
that is trained
on separate games
or is able to understand
different games
at the same time?
Or do we have separate policy
networks for different games?
And yeah, doesn't this like
text interface limit the model
in terms of communication?
If you're using
lectures, it might--
yeah, it might the bottom line.
I mean, I think ideally,
you go in this direction
where you have a
foundational model that works
for pretty much everything.
Does text-- I mean,
certainly, yeah, just
like a text in, text
out, limits what you can
do in terms of communication.
But hopefully, we
get beyond that.
I think it's a reasonable
choice for now.
Thank you.
I'm looking at more
Zoom questions.
So there's a question at chat.
Love to hear your
speculation on the future.
For instance, we've
seen some startups that
are fine-tuning LMs to
be biased or experts
in say subject x or subject y.
This seems like a
pretty general question.
I don't have strong
opinions on this.
Yeah.
I mean, I'm not too--
I'm not too focused myself
on fine-tuning language
models to specific tasks.
I think the direction
that I'm much more
interested in going forward
is the more general forms
of planning.
So I don't think I
can really comment
on how do you tune these
language models in these ways.
So what sort of
planning methods are you
interested in looking at?
Like, MCTS is one.
So let me-- sorry, I've got to
step out for just one second.
I've got to switch rooms.
Excuse me.
OK, never mind.
We're all good.
Sorry, what was the question?
Oh, yes.
I was just asking what
sort of planning algorithms
do you think are very
interesting to combine?
So I think we have
so many options,
like we have planning kind of
stuff, or auto, there's MCTS,
there's the bot you
did with Cicero.
So what do you think are the
most interesting algorithms
that you think will scale well?
Can you generalize?
Well, I think that's the big
question that a lot of people
are trying to figure out today.
And it's not really
clear what the answer is.
I mean, I think you look at
some of the chain of thought.
And I think there's
a lot of limitations
to chain of thought.
And I think that it should be
possible to do a lot better.
But it is really
impressive to see just
how general of an
approach it is.
And so I think it would
be nice to see things that
are general in that way, but
hopefully able to achieve
better performance.
Got it.
Ultimately, Cicero is like
an encoder-decoder model
in a sense that
encodes the model
and then you have the dialogue
model which is kind of decoder.
It was an encoder-decoder
model, yes.
I don't think that that's
necessarily the right choice.
But that's what we used.
Any questions?
OK, I think we're
are mostly good.
OK, thanks a lot.
OK.
Well, yeah, we all enjoyed it.
And if there are any questions,
feel free to email me,
reach out.
I'm happy to chat.